Well, come on!
Come on, old man!
Coming into Trinity Lane.
Eyes on the road, Brian!
Brian spies an opening!
Eyes on the staff! Hawking's lost it!
No!
You lose, Brian.
Too slow, old man. Too slow.
- Oh, my goodness.
- Right.
Time for a drink.
Hello.
Oo-pah!
What if the secret of the universe
had something to do with sex?
Maybe do your doctorate on that.
The physics of love.
- I think that's more your field, Brian.
- Oh, not lately.
They will boot you out, you know,
if you don't decide.
I know everyone here who's...
Brilliant.
Oh, dear. Scientists.
- Yes.
- You made it.
Don't worry, we don't have to stay for long.
Looks mortifyingly dull.
- Bores.
- Who's that?
Who's who?
Oh, him?
He's strange. Clever.
Goes to "Ban the Bomb" marches.
Wilde. Jane Wilde.
Oh, look, there's David. David!
- I'll be back in a minute.
- Diana! Diana!
- Hello.
- Science.
- Arts.
- English?
- French and Spanish.
What about you? What are you...
Oh, cosmologist, I'm a cosmologist.
What's that?
It's a kind of religion
for intelligent atheists.
Intelligent atheists?
- You're not religious, are you?
- C of E.
- Church of England?
- England, yeah.
I suppose someone has to be.
- What do cosmologists worship, then?
- What do we worship?
One single unifying equation that explains
everything in the universe.
- Really?
- Yes.
What's the equation?
That is the question.
And a very good question.
I'm not quite sure yet.
But I intend to find out.
Then why didn't you stay at Oxford?
Because my finals exams
were such a shambles,
that the examiners,
they summoned me in for a viva,
- and they told me that if I got a second...
- What's a viva?
Oh, it's a sort of mildly terrifying
face-to-face thingy.
- Like an interview?
- An interrogation.
And I told them that if they
gave me a second-class degree,
then I would stay with them
and do my research at Oxford.
But if they gave me the first that
I needed to get into Cambridge,
then they would never
have to see me again.
They gave you the first.
- They gave me a first.
- Of course.
This party is officially deceased.
Come on, I fixed up a ride home.
Come on, Jane.
Jane.
Well, it was lovely to talk to you.
Yes.
And I hope you find your equation.
Yes. Oh.
Bye.
- Stephen?
- Oh.
Yeah.
Well, then, here we are.
A little challenge for you all, as you embark
upon your separate doctoral journeys,
whatever they may be, Mr. Hawking.
Pass them down.
Something to separate the men
from the boys, the wheat from the chaff,
the mesons from the pi mesons,
the quarks from the quacks.
Ten questions, each more
impregnable than the last.
Good luck.
You'll need it.
Shall we say Friday, 3:00?
This is going to hospitalize me.
And, one. Drive! Two. Drive!
Three. Drive!
- Stay long, Brian.
- I'll give you something long.
Stay long, Brian! Keep long, Brian!
Shut up!
- Long, Brian!
- I'm exhausted!
Stay long, Brian!
Flip it. Flip it, Wiggs.
Somebody else, for once.
- Can I get two more of those, please?
- Yeah, sure.
- And some change for the payphone.
- Yeah.
- Steve, you all right, mate?
- Jane.
No, of course, Timothy turned out
to be an absolute cad.
I mean, you'll never guess who I saw
him with the other day. Caroline!
For heaven's sake,
she can have him, quite frankly.
What's the probability?
Reasonably low.
This is... This is Stephen.
- Do you play croquet?
- Croquet?
Not recently.
Sunday morning.
Actually busy Sunday mornings.
Him.
Okay.
Anyway, before I was
completely interrupted...
Oh, come on, get up.
How many did you get?
- Morning, Brian.
- Good afternoon, Stephen.
How many of the
impossible questions did you do?
Brian, I have no idea
what you're talking about.
How many of Sciama's questions
did you get, Stephen?
- None.
- You didn't get any?
I was going to do them later.
- You haven't even looked at them.
- No.
Stephen, are you aware that you have
voluntarily embarked upon a PhD in physics,
- at the most prestigious college in England?
- Yes.
I thought maybe you'd slept through
the induction or something.
- Bri?
- What?
- Can you whip on some Wagner?
- Oh, sod off.
- Come in, Stephen.
- Sorry.
Michael, that's so illegible,
I can't quite decipher how wrong it is.
I suspect enormously.
And, Brian, that's just baffling.
- Have you even bothered, Stephen?
- Oh, sorry.
Right. Train timetables.
That's totally unacceptable.
These expired a month ago.
It's on the back,
I had a little accident.
I could only do nine.
Good Lord.
Oh, thank God. Bravo.
Nine?
Come in.
Stephen, take a seat.
I wanted to talk to you
about your subject.
We're all rather concerned
as to what it's going to be.
I can't decide.
Do you have any ideas?
No.
So,
this is where J.J. Thomson
discovered the electron,
and where Rutherford split the atom.
You know, one of the great rewards
of this job is one never knows
from where the next great leap forward
is going to come, or from whom.
Listen, next Friday, I'm taking a
few graduates of merit to London
to attend a talk by the
mathematician Roger Penrose.
Do come along, if you're interested.
Oh, and close the door as you leave.
So, I gather you've
never been to church.
- Once upon a time.
- Tempted to convert?
I have a slight problem with the
whole "celestial dictator" premise.
Now, what are you doing for lunch?
Ma makes a cracking roast.
So, Jane, what are you studying?
- Arts.
- Spuds?
Thank you.
French and Spanish.
I'm hoping to do a PhD eventually.
Oh, what on?
Medieval poetry
of the Iberian Peninsula.
Medieval poets?
What painters do you like?
Well, I like Turner.
Turner, really? You know,
I always feel that his paintings
look as if they've been
left out in the rain.
Pa.
And William Blake.
- Thank you, Mother.
- Oh, good heavens, surely not.
- Jane, have some of my elderflower wine.
- Oh, yes, thank you.
Don't touch it. Don't touch it, Jane.
Thank you. Mother?
Stephen doesn't like my home-made wine.
Philistine. I'm going to send you back
with a couple of bottles.
So, Stephen, you have come
from church with a good woman.
Are you feeling holier than thou?
Positively saintly. Thank you.
You haven't said why
you don't believe in God.
A physicist can't allow his
calculations to be muddled
by a belief in a supernatural creator.
Sounds less of an argument
against God than against physicists.
Light or dark?
- Jane, light meat or dark?
- Oh, light, please.
I'm inviting Jane to be my
partner to the May Ball.
Really?
- Very impressive.
- You'll have to dance this year, Stephen.
Make way for Mother's leg. Here we go.
Hello.
Sorry.
- You okay?
- Yeah.
- Do you dance, Stephen?
- No.
No. I don't dance.
It's a phenomenon I'm very happy to observe,
but I can't possibly imagine participating.
I absolutely agree.
I mean, who would want to dance?
No, I'm serious. I don't dance.
No dancing, then.
You see how the men's shirtfronts
and their bow ties,
how they glow more than
the women's dresses?
Yes.
- Do you know why?
- Why?
- Tide.
- The washing powder?
The fluorescence in the washing powder
is caught by the UV light.
Why do you know that?
When stars are born,
and when... whe they die,
they emit UV radiation.
So if we could see the night sky
in the ultraviolet light,
then almost all the stars
would disappear
and all that we would see
are these spectacular births and deaths.
I reckon it would look a little...
Like that.
Wow!
Did you see?
Like those. Like those ones...
- Why?
- Why what?
Why Spanish medieval poetry?
I suppose I like to time-travel.
Like you.
Are there any particular time periods
that you like to visit?
- I imagine the Twenties was fun.
- The Roaring Twenties.
"Seek, then,
no learning from starry men,
"who follow with the optic glass
the whirling ways of stars that pass."
Bravo.
Well, that's astonishing, isn't it?
"In the beginning...
"was the Heaven and the Earth.
"And the Earth was without form,
"and darkness was upon
the face of the deep."
Will you dance with me?
The train now departing
from platform three
is the nine-seventeen service
to London King's Cross.
Come on, Stephen. Get a move on.
What's wrong with you, man? Chop-chop.
A star, more than three times
the size of our sun,
ought to end its life how?
With a collapse. The gravitational
forces of the entire mass
overcoming the electromagnetic
forces of individual atoms,
and so collapsing inwards.
If the star is massive enough,
it will continue this collapse,
creating a black hole,
where the warping of space-time is
so great that nothing can escape.
Not even light. It gets...
smaller.
Smaller.
The star, in fact, gets denser,
as atoms, even subatomic particles,
get literally crushed into
smaller and smaller space.
And at its end point,
what are we left with?
A space-time singularity.
Space and time come to a stop.
I wonder what would happen if you applied
Penrose's theory about black holes
to the entire universe.
If Einstein is right,
or if general relativity is correct,
then the universe is expanding, yes?
- Yes.
- Okay. So...
If you reverse time,
then the universe is getting smaller.
- All right.
- So,
what if I reverse the process
all the way back,
to see what happened at the
beginning of time itself?
- At the beginning of time itself?
- Yes. So the universe,
getting smaller and smaller,
getting denser and denser,
- hotter and hotter as we...
- You mean wind back the clock?
- Exactly. Wind back the clock.
- Wind back the clock.
Is that what you're doing?
- Are you winding back the clock?
- That is what I'm doing.
Well, keep winding.
And you've got quite a long way to go.
- Keep winding.
- I don't want to fall in.
You've got to get back
to the beginning of time.
You've got a long way to go.
Keep winding.
Keep winding until you get...
- A singularity?
- A space-time singularity.
So, the universe born
from a black hole exploding.
- Keep going.
- What do you mean, "Keep going"?
Before the universe began?
No, no, no, no. Keep going,
develop the mathematics.
Okay, all right, very good.
Push it as hard as you can. Push it.
- Push it. As hard as you can.
- I am pushing as hard as I can.
Why... Come on. One, two...
Why won't it...
All right, all right.
Fourth finger, fourth peg.
It's called motor neuron disease.
It's a progressive neurological disorder
that destroys the cells in the brain
that control essential muscle activity,
such as speaking,
walking...
breathing, swallowing.
The signals that muscles must receive
in order to move are disrupted.
The result is gradual muscle decay.
Wasting away.
Eventually, the ability to control
voluntary movement is lost.
Entirely.
I'm afraid average life expectancy
is two years.
There's nothing I can do for you.
What about the brain?
The brain isn't affected.
Your thoughts won't change, it's...
just that...
Well, eventually,
no one will know what they are.
I'm ever so sorry.
Hello, Brian.
Welcome to this week's episode
of The Natural World,
where this week we explore the
bizarre hibernation patterns
of the rare Cambridge physicist
seen here in his remarkable plumage.
So how was it? What did they say?
How's your wrist?
I have a disease, Bri.
Is it venereal, Stephen?
I have motor neuron disease.
Sorry, I don't...
It's Lou Gehrig's disease.
He was a baseball player.
Sorry, I'm lagging behind in
my pioneering research into
obscure, motor,
baseball-related diseases.
I have two years to live.
Sorry?
It does sound odd when you
say it out loud, doesn't it?
You... What do you mean?
No, you don't.
What did they say?
Sorry, I don't really...
Will you go, Bri?
Stephen, sorry, I was just
being a berk. I didn't...
No, it's not...
Will you go?
Stephen, phone for you.
It's a girl.
I'll... I'll...
I'll see you soon. I'll...
Yes.
She's waiting.
Stephen?
Nobody's seen him for a while.
I suppose, you know...
Jane. Jane.
Brian, hello. Sorry.
Why don't you... Why don't you sit down?
I'm so sorry.
I spoke to Stephen, yesterday,
and I know that you called him...
Something educational?
Very.
John is having an affair with Martha.
But... Martha is in love with Alan,
and I think that Alan is probably a
homosexual by the look of his jumper. So...
Well, I'm just trying to work out the
mathematical probability of happiness.
Are you close?
Some integer of zero, but no,
not quite there yet.
Stephen.
You just missed him,
he was here earlier.
Don't do this.
Go.
Croquet.
Play a game with me.
Go.
If you don't get up
and play a game with me,
I won't come back here again.
Ever.
Come on.
Leave me now.
- Are you going to talk about this or not?
- Will you just go?
- Is that what you want?
- Yes, it is what I want.
So, please, if you care about
me at all, then please just go.
- I can't.
- I have two years to live.
- I need to work.
- I love you.
That's a false conclusion.
I want us to be together
for as long as we've got,
and if that's not very long, well,
then that's just how it is. It'll have to do.
You don't know what's coming.
It'll affect everything.
Your glasses are always dirty.
There.
That's better, isn't it?
Yes.
Yes, it is.
Now the solutions
to the Schrödinger equation
must vanish at the boundary
of the box, and so we have...
Time.
Oh, time, that's your subject?
Any aspect in particular?
Time.
Come in, come in.
I... don't think you realize
what lies ahead, Jane.
His life is going to be very short.
So, be careful.
The weight of science is against you,
and this will not be a fight, Jane.
This is going to be a very heavy defeat.
For all of us.
I know what you all think. That...
That I don't look like
a terribly strong person.
But I love him,
and he loves me.
We're going to fight
this illness together.
All of us.
Two, three...
Good luck.
- Morning, Stephen.
- Morning, Professor.
I know, I know.
- It could be a little bit more elegant.
- Yes, but I...
I understand...
Come in, Stephen.
I know it's something we were
all worried about initially,
but I... I knew, Roger...
You had some reservations
about it in the early days.
Yes, but it's not uncommon
in any theory.
Yes.
- Absolutely.
- Very well, very well. We'll see.
- Welcome, Stephen.
- Morning.
- Would you like to take a seat?
- No, I'm fine. Thank you.
- You're sure?
- Yeah.
So, Stephen, in summary,
as we know, chapter one, full of holes,
lacks mathematical support.
Professor Thorne?
Chapter two, not really original.
Uses a lot of Roger's ideas.
Well, at least you run with them.
Chapter three,
too many unanswered questions.
I agree.
And then, of course,
we have chapter four.
This black hole
at the beginning of time.
- Space-time singularity.
- Indeed.
It's brilliant.
Brilliant, Stephen. Superb.
Therefore, all there is
to say is well done.
Or perhaps I should say,
to be more precise, well done, Doctor.
Bravo, Stephen.
An extraordinary theory.
Thank you.
- So, what next?
- Prove it.
To prove with a single equation
that time has a beginning.
Wouldn't that be nice, Professor?
The one simple, elegant equation
to explain everything.
Yes, it would.
It would indeed.
Thank you.
To the esteemed and formidable
- Doctor...
- Who?
Doctor Stephen Hawking.
Thank you.
It is astonishing he's the first
person to receive his doctorate
bearing in mind how little
work he's been doing.
Work was the worst
four-letter word for Stephen.
At Oxford especially, he averaged an hour.
An hour a day, he averaged.
And now, here he is, the esteemed man.
- Astonishing levels of sloth.
- I've got... on the theme of sloth, Brian,
how many of your lectures have
I covered in the last six months?
When you've been doing research
trips up to the Lake District.
- Absolutely, completely...
- So have I!
- How many?
- Four.
- Everything all right?
- All good. I'm fine.
- What can you do?
- Would you like kartoffel?
Oh, please.
- Business or pleasure?
- For pleasure.
Hey, Robbie.
It's okay, Robbie.
This
is
temporary.
Of course.
Well, it's convenient for breakfast.
Thank you.
Sorry, did you say something?
I said...
Yes?
...thank you.
There we go, Lucy.
There we go.
Have you got her?
She looks like you.
Oh, no.
Oh, wait. Go, Jane.
I'll be one second.
Luce! Lucy.
Jane?
Oh, Stephen. Oh. Hello.
I've got an idea.
Jane... Jane, I've had an idea.
- Hello.
- Hello, Dennis.
- How are you?
- Okay. Good luck.
- He'll be fine. He'll be fine.
- Oops. Sorry.
- No problem.
Allowing us to predict
that some particles can,
in fact, escape a black hole.
So, black holes are not,
in fact, black at all,
but glow with heat radiation.
The steady emission of heat energy
causes the black holes to lose mass
and eventually they disappear
in a spectacular explosion.
It's very, very simple,
in the way that a body loses heat.
- Second law of thermodynamics.
- Right, it's thermodynamics.
If we can imagine that a black hole
is, indeed, losing particles
and over time, will diminish in size,
it will evaporate, it will...
Disappear.
So...
First
a star vanishes into a black hole.
And then
the black hole itself
vanishes.
Gone, nothing.
- From nothing to nothing!
- You owe me another beer.
I have just shown you that our friend has
proven that time, indeed, has a beginning.
Not only that,
how the universe was born, and...
- How it will end.
- Bang!
Crunch!
It's, beautiful, it's racy, it's...
Complete nonsense!
It's preposterous!
Was it something I said, Professor?
Excuse me.
My name...
My name is Professor Khalatnikov
from the Soviet Academy of Science.
As you know,
my field is evolution
of the hot universe,
the properties of the microwave
background radiation
and the theory of black holes.
To be honest,
I came here today
expecting to hear a lot of nonsense.
I go home disappointed.
The little one here
has done it!
He has done it!
It is a pleasure to meet you, Professor.
Entirely my pleasure. My pleasure.
- Thank you.
- Well done, Stephen.
Well, that went pretty well,
all things considered.
I was worried for a while.
- Hawking radiation!
- The little one has done it!
The little one has done it!
- Hey, come on, genius!
- Oh, very funny!
You've had enough of that, old man.
Come on, codger.
One, two, three!
My God! How does Jane manage?
Stephen,
your motor-mouth disease,
does it affect...
What?
Everything?
What? No. Different system.
- Automatic.
- Are you serious?
Well, that's pretty wonderful, isn't it?
Well, it certainly
explains a lot about men.
Hurry up!
Come on!
Please.
What is it?
It's a surprise.
Right.
Keep them closed.
Ta-da!
Look, Daddy, look!
That is an electric wheelchair.
If you don't like it, we can take it back.
I don't understand. You've spent years
assuming black holes exist
and you believe Cygnus X-1
could well turn out to be the first
black hole that we can actually observe.
And yet, you've bet Kip Thorne
it's not a black hole.
- Yes.
- What did you bet him?
A one-year subscription to a magazine.
- Which magazine? Nature?
- No.
Penthouse.
- Penthouse?
- Yes.
Gonna get you!
Daddy, look out! Let's get Mummy!
Come on...
Gonna get you.
Mummy, Mummy! Come and look!
We're gonna get you.
Come on.
Holiday!
- Holiday!
Holiday! Holiday...
- Hello!
- Hello.
- There you are.
- Hello, Pa!
- Isn't it marvelous?
- What about these steps, Frank?
- Steps are nothing, Jane.
- Stephen! Here we are!
- Hello!
Yes, here we go. Once we're up at the top,
it's very snug. Hello, Stephen.
- Hello.
- There we go.
- Turn you around, Stephen.
- Want me to pull?
No, no, I'll be fine. You get the luggage.
Here we go. Off we go. Let's go.
There we are, you see? Quite easy.
Up one, there we go.
Shimmering?
- The... Oh, rain coming down, shivering cold?
- Cold?
No. The... falling.
Falling...
- Very cold.
- What is it? I... I'm...
having a jolly...
Okay, take Lucy. One minute.
What is it?
Is it out?
- Some... some water?
- No, don't worry.
Okay, that's it. There we go.
It's okay. It's okay.
He needs to see a specialist.
Keeps happening over and over again.
- Ridiculous.
- No doctors.
No doctors.
All right, no doctors.
A little water.
Stephen.
I need help.
If only for Robert.
He's missing out on his childhood.
I keep looking for a way
to make this work, but...
I can't find it on my own.
Everything is fine.
We're just a normal family.
We're not a normal family.
We're not a normal family!
Robert.
Your mother is very angry with me.
Thanks.
Jane.
Jane, stop.
Sit.
Now,
I'd like to make a suggestion.
Might sound a bit unusual,
but I have seen it work wonders.
I think
that you should consider joining
the church choir.
Mum,
I think that's possibly the most English
thing anyone has ever said.
Maybe so.
- I used to love singing.
- You're very good at it.
I don't know about that.
Just go.
It's one hour a week.
Really lovely, everyone.
Okay. See you next week.
- Bye-bye.
- Bye.
Good-bye.
- Hello.
Have you come to sing?
I just came to...
- Soprano?
- Mezzo.
Lovely, just what we need.
Where have you been hiding?
Good question.
Well, you're here now, and...
just in time, as they say.
Oh, you know, I have to
come back anyway, so...
- Good.
- You have everything?
- Yes, thank you. Yes.
- Thank you for coming.
You will be a valuable asset.
Thank you.
Well, I should be going.
And if your son wants
those piano lessons, just...
- Yes, yes, absolutely. I...
- Call me.
- I will do.
- Great.
My husband adores music, too.
Oh, well, I could... Does he play?
I could teach him, as well.
That's a long story.
- But...
- Okay.
- Well, thank you, Jonathan.
- My pleasure, Jane. See you again.
- Bye-bye.
Third finger. No, that...
That one, there.
Try lifting your wrists a little bit.
Keep your elbows back. Okay, try again.
No.
- Yeah.
- Good.
More wine?
Why not? Thank you.
- Stephen?
- No.
Stephen, Jane was telling me
that you have a beautiful, theorem.
That proves that the universe,
had a beginning. Is that it?
That was my PhD thesis.
My new project disproves it.
- Disproves it?
- Yes.
So then you no longer believe
in the creation?
What one believes
is irrelevant in physics.
"Irrelevant in physics."
I see.
Stephen's done a U-turn.
The big new idea is that the universe
has no boundaries at all.
No boundaries, no beginning.
And no God.
Oh, I see. I... I thought that...
you'd proved the universe had a beginning
and thus a need for a creator.
My mistake.
No, mine.
Stephen is looking for a single theory
that explains all the forces in the universe.
Therefore, God must die.
Oh, why must God die? I don't see.
The two great pillars of physics
are quantum theory,
the laws that govern the very
small particles, electrons and so on,
and general relativity.
Yes, Einstein.
Einstein's theory, the laws that govern
the very large planets and such.
But quantum and relativity...
Don't tell me. They're different?
They don't remotely
play by the same rules.
If the world were all potatoes,
then, easy.
You could trace a precise beginning
as Stephen once did.
A moment of creation.
Hallelujah. God lives.
If you incorporate peas into the menu,
well, then it all goes a little...
Tits up.
Yes. Haywire.
- It just all becomes a godless mess.
- Oh, dear.
Einstein hated peas.
Quantum theory. He said,
"God doesn't play dice with the universe."
Seems he not only plays dice,
but he throws them
where we can't find them.
God is back on
the endangered species list.
Well, I expect he'll cope.
And physics is back in business.
Yes.
Physics is back in business.
I was... married, actually.
But, sadly, she passed.
Almost a year ago now.
It was... leukemia.
She fought it and I nursed her. But...
in the end...
I do get quite lonely.
The... tyranny of the empty room
and all that.
But music is my salvation.
Teaching and playing.
Not really as a career, but I'm not
very ambitious. Though that's not...
Is that a sin? I don't know.
Wrong man to ask.
Thank you so much for having me.
- Thank you for coming.
- It was really, really wonderful.
If there's anything I can do
to be of service, to you,
to the family, I mean,
I would consider it a privilege.
I have no children or commitments, so...
I only mean that if I could be of help,
I believe I might find
a purpose that would...
help alleviate my own, situation.
Good night.
Night.
I understand
if you need help.
If someone is
prepared to offer it,
I won't object.
- Chilly?
- Yeah, it's very bracing.
Come on. Ready?
- Yeah.
- All right.
17, 18...
There we go. Right.
I'm going to put the kettle on.
Calls you one and calls you all
To gain his everlasting hall
Christ was born to save
Great, lovely, okay. We can go.
Just gone 7:45.
- Could you all leave your copies?
- Good-bye.
There's something I need to tell you.
What?
I'm pregnant.
Gosh, I, assumed that you and Stephen...
Well, that's really wonderful.
- It is.
- Yes, wonderful.
Congratulations, Jane.
Thank you.
Everyone say, "Cheese." Ready?
On the count of three. One, two, three.
Cheese!
Cheese.
Is that your brother? On his bike?
- Mummy!
- Just coming.
Oh, come on, sweetie. Come on...
Now, you know
I've always been supportive of
your choice not to have home help,
but we need to find
a permanent solution.
This... this...
situation cannot continue.
You need to have a proper
live-in nurse immediately.
We have help.
Look, you know what I'm talking about.
We can't afford a live-in nurse.
Stephen, you need to find a way
for your family's sake.
You're world-famous.
For black holes, not for rock concerts.
Stephen, this isn't funny.
I believe it's urgent.
We do have a right to know.
We have a right to know, Jane.
Know what?
Whose child Timothy is.
Stephen's or Jonathan's.
That's what you think of me.
There's no way that Timothy could have
any other father than Stephen.
None.
- Jonathan. Please don't go.
- I have to go. Come on. Everyone is talking.
So, what does it matter?
It's difficult for me
because I'm just trying to help.
I know you're trying to help,
and your help is valued.
The best thing for me right now is...
I think maybe if...
- I just step back for now.
- Please, Jonathan. We need you.
The children need you, and I need you,
and Stephen needs you. Jonathan.
There's other things as well. Jane, I...
I have feelings for you.
And I have feelings for you, too.
Thank you, Jane.
I've been invited to the Bordeaux Opera.
Invited where?
Bordeaux.
To Bordeaux?
Wagner.
The students can take me.
I know you hate flying.
I do hate to fly.
Bring the car.
Meet me in Bordeaux.
Take the children camping.
It'll be too difficult
to manage, Stephen.
Bring Jonathan.
I doubt he would be willing.
Hello, Stephen.
Is this okay?
Well...
I won't tell if you won't.
Just...
bearing in mind you have to drive.
Jane needs help.
Sarah, you won't forget a vitamin
B injection as soon as you land.
- No. Of course.
- And you'll call me when you get to the hotel?
- I will.
- Yes? Promise?
- Yes.
- Good.
Stephen.
Mum will take the baby.
- She'll be here any minute.
- See you in Bordeaux.
And be good.
- Are they asleep?
- Yeah.
- Okay. It's okay. I'm all right.
- Where are the children?
I think we've done rather well.
Right. Children? Get your sleeping bags.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thanks.
Jonathan?
Oh, God!
Excuse me, sorry.
Jonathan?
Jonathan.
Stephen's been taken ill.
He's in hospital and...
- he... he's in a coma.
- Stephen's been taken ill?
What are you talking about?
This way would be a painless end.
If we try to bring him round
from the anesthetic,
it's not sure
he will survive resuscitation.
You have to bring him round
from the anesthetic.
Are you sure it's what you want?
The only way of weaning him off the
ventilator will be to give him a tracheotomy.
A hole in the neck,
bypassing the throat.
He will never speak again.
There's no question.
Stephen must live.
I will see he gets everything he needs.
I will have him transferred
back to Cambridge.
He may not survive the journey.
Yes, he will.
I know.
I'll...
step back.
Did you get everything in the car?
His chair and his equipment and everything?
Good-bye.
Stephen?
This is a spelling board.
Firstly, you tell me what letter
you want by blinking
when I say the color of the group
that contains the letter.
Once I know the group, you can choose
the character inside that group
by blinking again when I say the color
of each letter within that group.
Apparently.
Let's just try.
Green.
Blue.
Pink.
Black.
Red.
Blink to choose the color of the group
of the letter you want, Stephen.
Green.
Blue.
Pink.
Black.
Red.
Hello, Elaine.
- Shall I take your coat?
- Okay.
Thank you, Jane.
- Just wait here.
- Great.
She's here.
She comes highly recommended.
Promise not to eat her alive.
Okay?
Here we are.
Elaine, Stephen.
- Stephen, Elaine.
- Lovely to meet you, Professor.
Now, you should have
everything you need.
But if there's anything else,
I'll be just next door.
Great.
I think we'll get straight to work.
Thank you, Jane.
- Oh, if you could close the doors.
- Of course.
We'll get started, then.
Okay.
Red.
Yellow.
T.
Green.
Black. E.
Green, green. A.
Tea.
You want a cup of tea.
Okay.
Any preference?
You've memorized the board,
I know you have.
I haven't got all day.
Green, green.
Green, yellow.
Yellow. B.
Green, blue, pink, black, red.
Red.
Green, yellow, blue, blue.
U. So, B, U.
Builder's tea, right?
So, how did you get on?
You know... I think he's the
most brilliant man I've ever met.
- You're very lucky.
- Thank you.
- You must worship the ground beneath...
- His wheels?
And he's the perfect patient.
He's so funny!
- When you read about him...
- Let's see how you get on, shall we, Elaine?
That's tightened up.
As you can see, it's height-adjustable
and we can change the angle
to whatever Steve wants it at.
- You know, it's cutting-edge.
- So, how does it work?
It uses a very simple interface
that scans through the alphabet,
selects each letter one at a time.
I mean, using this technique,
the Professor can expect to write
about four words per minute.
Good. Better than one a minute.
Yes, and what I've done
is taken the components from a
telephone answering system, actually,
to convert the written text
into synthesized speech.
I mean, the voice sounds
a little bit robotic, but...
shall we give it a try?
- Great.
- Here's the clicker.
Right hand?
There you go.
Welcome to the future.
It's American.
Is that a problem?
Oh, my goodness.
Well, is there another voice?
That's the only one
they have at the moment.
I think it's great.
Frankly, my dear, I don't give a damn.
Exterminate.
I will write a book.
About what?
Time.
What is the nature of time?
Will it ever come to an end?
Someday, these answers
may seem as obvious to us
as the Earth orbiting the sun,
or perhaps as ridiculous
as a tower of tortoises.
Only time, whatever that may be,
will tell.
Professor?
- It is for a friend.
- Of course it is.
That's what they all say.
You don't have to be embarrassed
in front of me, Professor.
I know what men are like.
Shall we take a look?
There you go.
Oh! I'm sorry.
Next one?
What?
So I said, "I have long been looking
for a model of the universe.
"I finally found her."
I bet you did.
Stephen, I need to steal you.
The contract's arrived.
Could you just give us
a minute, please, Jane?
There we go.
Like new.
"Who are we?
"Why are we here?
"If we ever learn this, it will be
the ultimate triumph of human reason,
"for then we would know
the mind of God."
Do you mean this?
Yes.
- Of course.
- So, you're acknowledging him?
However...
"However" what?
Are you actually going to
let me have this moment?
You are welcome.
I have asked Elaine
to travel with me to America.
She will look after me.
Will she?
Yes.
You always used to tell me
when an invitation came in.
Another award. What can you do?
I am sorry.
How many years?
They said two.
You've had so many.
Everything will be okay.
I have loved you.
I did my best.
Careful.
- That... That's staying.
- All right.
Bye, Jonathan.
Professor, I love your book!
Thank you.
I first met the Professor
in 1963.
Now there you are.
Time! Where does it go?
It has been one of the great joys
of my life to watch this man
defy every expectation,
both scientific and personal.
Please welcome onto the stage
my esteemed colleague,
my dear friend, Professor Hawking.
Thank you. Could we please have the first
pre-selected question? Thank you.
Can you hear me?
Now you are recognized everywhere.
How do you deal with all the attention?
I was stopped recently
by a tourist in Cambridge,
who asked if I was
the real Stephen Hawking.
I replied I was not and said the
real one was much better looking.
In 1979, you talked about the possibility
of a theory of everything
being discovered before
the end of the century.
I now predict that I was wrong.
Professor Hawking, you have said
you do not believe in God.
Do you have a philosophy
of life that helps you?
You have said you do not believe in God.
Do you have a philosophy
of life that helps you?
It is clear that we are just
an advanced breed of primates
on a minor planet orbiting around
a very average star
in the outer suburb
of one among 100 billion galaxies.
But,
ever since the dawn of civilization,
people have craved for an understanding
of the underlying order of the world.
There ought to be
something very special
about the boundary conditions
of the universe.
And what can be more special
than that there is no boundary...
And there should be no boundary
to human endeavor.
We are all different.
However bad life may seem,
there is always something
you can do and succeed at.
While there is life, there is hope.
That came.
It's from Stephen.
Gosh.
Your glasses are always dirty.
Professor and Mrs. Hawking,
Her Majesty the Queen.
Congratulations...
My Companion of Honour.
Not bad for an old liberal socialist.
Don't worry,
you can decline the knighthood.
Thank you, for today.
It was extraordinary.
It's all been rather
extraordinary though, hasn't it?
What are you writing?
Look what we made.