We've become bored with watching
actors give us phoney emotions.
We're tired of pyrotechnics
and special effects.
While the world he inhabits is,
in some respects, counterfeit. -
- There's nothing fake
about Truman himself.
No scripts, no cue cards.
It isn't always Shakespeare,
but it's genuine. It's a life.
I'm not gonna make it. You're
gonna have to go on without me.
No way, mister.
You're going to the top of
this mountain, broken legs and all.
Many viewers
leave him on all night, for comfort.
You're crazy, you know that?
For me there's no difference between
private life and public life.
My life is The Truman Show.
The Truman Show is a lifestyle.
It's a noble life.
It is... a truly blessed life.
Tell me something I don't know.
All right.
Promise me one thing, though.
If I die before the summit, use me
as an alternative source of food.
You're gross.
It's all real.
Nothing you see on the show is fake.
It's merely controlled.
THE TRUMAN SHOW
Eat me, dammit. That's an order.
Maybe just your love handles.
I have love handles?
Yeah, little ones.
- Truman, you're gonna be late.
- Okay!
DAY 10,909
- Good morning!
And in case I don't see you,
good afternoon and good night.
- Morning, Truman.
- Morning, Spencer. Hey, Pluto.
- He won't hurt you.
- I know. It's just me.
Come on, Pluto.
What is it?
An aircraft began shedding parts
as it flew over Sea haven -
- A few moments ago.
Luckily, no one was hurt.
How do you feel today...?
That's good.
- Thinking of flying somewhere?
- Nope.
This is classical Klyne.
Forget about the perils of flying -
- And let this music calm you down.
"Dog Fancy', please.
Thank you very much.
Get me a paper, will you, Errol?
And one of these for the wife.
Loves her fashion mags.
- That be all for you, Truman?
- That's the whole kit and caboodle.
- Hank!
- Good morning, Truman.
Good morning, Truman.
Beautiful day, isn't it?
- Hows your lovely wife?
- Good. Yours?
Couldn't be better.
- Nice talking to you.
- You too. Think about that policy.
Two for one. That's a good deal.
Doppelganger special.
Hey, fellas.
Going in? Go ahead.
- Go ahead.
- I'm not that anxious to get there.
Could I have directory assistance
for Fiji, please? Fiji Islands.
Truman, did you see this?
I'm sorry, ma'am. If he's in a coma
he's probably uninsurable.
Yes, Fiji. Do you have a listing
for Lauren Garland?
Nothing listed...
Do you have a Sylvia Garland?
S for Sylvia.
Nothing...
Okay, thank you.
- Lawrence.
- I've got a prospect in Wells Park.
Wells Park?
On... Harbour Island?
- You know another one?
- I can't. I have an appointment.
Dentist, or... yeah.
You'll lose more than your teeth
if you don't meet your quota.
They're making cutbacks
at the end of this month.
You need this. Besides, a half hour
across the bay will do you good.
Thanks.
Hello. Ferry's still here, huh?
Thought I might have missed it.
- One way or return?
- Return.
There you go, sir.
- Do you need any help, sir?
- You go ahead, I'll be fine.
Hi, honey.
Look what I got free at
the checkout. It's a "Chef's Pal".
It's a dicer, grater, peeler, all in
one. No sharpening, dishwater-safe.
Wow... that's amazing.
Truman... you missed a spot.
That is a beer.
- I'm thinking about getting out.
- Yeah? Out of what?
Out of my job. Out of Sea haven.
Off this island. Out.
What the hell's wrong with your job?
You've got a great job. A desk job.
I'd kill for a desk job.
You should try stocking vending
machines. Now there's excitement.
- Don't you ever get antsy?
- Where's there to go?
- Fiji.
- Where's Fiji? Near Florida?
See here? This is us...
And all the way
around here... Fiji.
You can't get any further away
before you start coming back.
There's still islands in Fiji where
no human being has ever set foot.
So when are you gonna go?
It's not that simple.
It takes money, planning...
- You can't just up and go.
- Right.
I'm gonna do it,
don't worry about that.
Bonus time
is just around the corner.
- Are you coming for a drink?
- No, I can't tonight.
I don't like that weather, son.
We should head back.
Just a bit farther. Please?
- Okay.
- Yes!
Daddy!
You're soaked.
Where have you been?
- We can scrape together 8,000...
- You and Marlon...
- We can bum around the world.
- And then what?
- You're talking like a teenager.
- Maybe I feel like a teenager.
We have mortgage payments. Do we
just walk away from our obligations?
- It would be an adventure.
- We were going to try for a baby.
- Isn't that enough of an adventure?
- That can wait.
I want to get away.
See some of the world. Explore!
You want to be an explorer...
This will pass.
We all think like this now and then.
Let's get you out
of these wet clothes. Come to bed.
You never see anything. They always
turn the camera and play music.
The wind blows, the curtain moves.
You don't see anything.
"Dog Fancy', please.
Thank you.
Paper, Earl, please.
I might as well get one of these.
- For the wife?
- She's got to have them.
- Anything else, Truman?
- That's the whole ball of wax.
Dad?
Hey, what are you doing?
Get out of the way!
Stop those people!
Stop! Stop!
Open the door! Somebody
stop the bus! Stop the bus!
Somebody stop it!
Stop the bus!
It doesn't sound insane at all.
I see him ten times a week.
I almost hugged a perfect stranger
in the salon...
It was Dad.
Dressed like a homeless man.
And a businessman and a lady
with a dog forced him onto a bus.
It's about time they cleaned up
the trash downtown.
They never found Dad's body.
If it wasn't him, it was his twin!
Did Dad have a brother?
You know perfectly well
that your father was an only child.
Just like you.
Sweetie... You're just feeling bad
because of what happened.
You sailing off into that storm...
But I've never blamed you.
And I don't blame you now.
Truman...?
What are you doing down here?
Fixing the mower.
- I saw my father today.
- I know.
Your mother called.
You shouldn't upset her like that.
- What did you want?
- I made macaroni.
- I'm not hungry.
- You know...
We ought to throw out that mower.
Get one of those new Elk Rotaries.
What's he doing?
They got rid of her,
but they couldn't erase the memory.
10,910
NUMBER OF DAYS RUNNING
- Are you okay?
- Excuse me. Sorry I fell on you.
I've been such a klutz all day.
I must have sprained this ankle.
- I'm so sorry to fall on you.
- Don't worry about it.
- I'm Meryl.
- Hi, I'm Truman.
- Truman, you've studied enough.
- I've got to commit this to memory.
Come on, an ice-cold brew sky.
You're gonna have to copy off me,
so be careful.
You're a better person than I am.
- See you later.
- Bye.
See you later, loser.
Hi.
- Konnichi-wa.
- What?
- You take Japanese.
- Oh, yes...
Lauren, right?
- It's on the...
- Lauren, right.
- I'm Truman Burbank.
- Yeah, I know.
- I'm not allowed to talk to you.
- Really?
- I'm a pretty dangerous character.
- I'm sorry. It's not up to me.
Girls have got to be careful.
- You have a boyfriend, right?
- It's not that.
Was it Meryl, the girl I was with?
We're not... We're just friends.
- It's nothing like that.
- It's how I look? Not your type?
No.
HOW'S IT GOING TO END?
I was wondering that myself.
Would you maybe, possibly
sometime go out for some pizza?
- Like, Friday? Saturday?
- I can't.
Sunday, Monday, Tuesday?
NOW
- We have finals tomorrow.
- Yeah, I know.
If we don't go now,
it won't happen. Do you understand?
So what do you want to do?
Please keep your hands
inside the car!
This is my favorite pizza place.
Tony, one large, extra plankton!
We have so little time.
They'll be here any minute.
- They don't want me talking to you.
- Then don't talk.
They're here.
- What do they want?
- Listen to me.
Everybody knows everything you do.
They're pretending. Understand?
- My name's not Lauren, it's Sylvia.
- Lauren, sweetheart, not again.
- Who are you?
- Her father.
I've never seen him before.
Truman, don't listen to him.
Everything I've told you
is the truth.
It's fake. It's all for you. The sky
and the sea. Everything is a set!
Please, don't listen to him.
He's gonna lie to you.
- I want to know what's going on.
- Schizophrenia. We've tried it all.
Hypnotism, shock therapy...
Don't worry, you're not the first.
- She brings all her boys down here.
- Truman, he's lying!
Get out of here. Come and find me.
- I'll see you in school.
- We're moving to Fiji.
Sylvia! Hey!
- Why didn't he just follow her?
- His mother got really sick.
He couldn't leave her.
He's kind. Maybe he's too kind.
I can't believe he married Meryl
on the rebound.
Come on, Sal. We've already got this
on the greatest hits tape.
HOW'S IT GOING TO END?
Close, but no cigar.
Another beautiful day in paradise.
But don't forget to buckle up.
He's heading west on Stuart.
Stand by, all extras.
He's turning onto Lancaster Square.
My God, he nearly hither! Something
is wrong. Change frequencies.
Sorry about that, folks. I guess
we picked up a police frequency.
It's classical Klyne, and we've
still got some great music ahead.
But buckle up. Remember safety.
A good driver is a safe driver.
CRACKDOWN ON HOMELESS
City Fathers: "Enough is Enough"
- Can I help?
- I have an appointment.
- What's happening?
- Nothing.
- Just tell me what's happening.
- We're remodeling.
- It's none of your business.
- Tell me, or I'll report you!
You're trespassing.
- Marlon!
- Truman, what are you doing here?
I've got to talk to you.
I'm on to something big!
- You look like shit.
- I think I'm mixed up in something.
A lot of strange things
have been happening.
The people on the elevator,
there was no backing on it...
And the radio starts following me,
talking about everything I'm doing.
- This is one of your fantasies.
- I think this is about my dad.
I think he's alive. I'll tell you
about it later. I'm being followed.
Who?
It's hard to tell.
They look like regular people.
- How about those two?
- Could be.
It's when I'm unpredictable.
That's when they can't...
Anything happen...?
We have to get out of here.
- You ready to go?
- I can't.
- You're gonna get us both fired.
- Okay then, let's do it.
Whatever you say, I'm game.
Your birthday comes but once a year!
Maybe I'm being set up
for something.
You ever think that your whole life
has been building toward something?
No.
When you were hauling chickens,
how far did you get off the island?
I went all over. Never found
a place like this, though.
Look at that sunset. It's perfect.
That's the big guy.
Quite a paintbrush he's got.
Just between you and me, Marlon...
- I'm going away for a while.
- Really?
My little clown...
Old carrot-top.
The best photos...
- We should be getting you home.
- Here's us at Mt. Rushmore.
Do you remember, Truman?
You slept the whole way there.
- It looks so small.
- Things do, when you look back.
Look, Truman.
The happiest day of our lives.
- Look! Jean, Jodie, Joanne...
- Doesn't she look beautiful?
Well, she still does.
There's room for baby photos. I want
to hold a grandchild before I go.
We really should get you home.
No, you stay. Relax.
- Your favorite show is coming on.
- And we have something to discuss.
- A certain person's birthday.
- Oh, I see.
There'll be another "Lucy" tomorrow.
Now it's time for Golden Oldies.
Tonight we present the classic:
"Show Me the Way to Go Home".
You don't have to leave home to
discover what the world is about.
We learn that no one is poor
who has friends.
Full of laughter, love, pain,
sadness, but ultimately, redemption.
The cherry scene will have you
split ting your sides with laughter.
There'll be tears, too, when
David and Jennifer are reunited.
Let's join the Abbots
in Camden Village.
Thank you, Sweetie.
I need to talk to you,
but let's go outside.
- I'd love to, but I'm really late.
- What's your rush?
There was that elevator disaster.
It was on the news.
The cable just snapped.
The elevator plummeted ten flights.
Right next door to where you work.
What if you had been in there?
Anyway, I have an amputation on
one of the women from the elevator.
She's very young. It's sad.
Wish me luck.
I'll cross my fingers for you.
Excuse me. May I help you?
I'm looking for my wife,
Nurse Burbank. It's very important.
That's not possible.
She's in pre-op.
Sure... Okay, fine.
Can you pass along a message?
I had to go to Fiji.
I'll call when I get there.
- When you get to Fiji?
- You got it.
- Fine. I'll tell her.
- Thank you so much.
Sorry.
Let me help you with that.
He's here.
Scalpel.
I'm now making
my primary incision. -
- Just above the right knee.
- Nicely done.
- Unless you're family...
- It's just a beautiful job.
- I'll let someone else tidy up.
TRAVELLERS BEWARE
IT COULD HAPPEN TO YOU!
- I'm sorry to keep you.
- That's okay.
- How can I help?
- I'd like a flight to Fiji.
- When would you like to leave?
- Today.
I'm sorry. I don't have anything
for at least a month.
It's the busy season.
Do you want to book the flight?
I'll make other arrangements.
Last call for Chicago!
All aboard!
Thank you.
Windy City, here we come.
Hi!
Hello...
- Mom, isn't that you know you?
- Face the front.
Everybody off, we've got a problem.
I'm sorry, son.
- Wasn't his father from Chicago?
- His father was from Des Moines.
- Why does he want to go to Chicago?
- He's not going anywhere.
Truman?
- Honey, are you okay?
- Get in.
- Truman...
- Look.
I predict that, in just a moment,
we'll see a lady on a red bike -
- Followed by a man with flowers and
a Volkswagen with a dented fender.
- Truman, please...
- Look!
Lady...
Flowers...
- And...?
- And...
- Truman, this is silly.
- There's the dented Beetle! Yes!
You know how I did that?
They're on a loop.
They go around the block, they
come back, they go around again.
- I invited Marlon to barbecue...
- I won't be here.
We need more charcoal.
Are you listening
to a word I'm saying?
You're upset
because you want to go to Fiji?
Okay, go.
I think you should save
for a few months, and then go.
I'm going to take a shower.
Let's go now.
I'm ready. Why wait?
Early bird gathers no moss,
rolling stone catches the worm.
Truman, what are you doing?
- Truman...
- Where shall we go?
- Truman, where are we going?
- I guess I'm being spontaneous.
Somebody help me!
I'm being spontaneous!
Forget Fiji.
We can't drive to Fiji, can we?
- What about Atlantic City.
- No, you hate to gamble.
That's right, I do.
But I never have.
And that's why people go places.
- I think I'm going to throw up.
- Me, too.
Blocked at every turn. Beautifully
synchronized, don't you think?
- You're blaming me for the traffic?
- Should I?
Truman, let's go home.
You're right.
We could be stuck here for hours.
It'll be like this all the way
to Atlantic City. Let's go back.
I'm sorry.
I don't know what got into me.
- Can you please slow down?
- Yes, I can.
- That's our turn-off.
- I changed my mind.
What's New Orleans like
this time of year? Mardis Gras!
Look, Meryl. Same road, no cars.
It's magic.
Let me out. If you want to
destroy yourself, do it on your own.
I think I'd like a little company.
Oh, Truman...
You knew this would happen.
You know you can't drive over water.
Let's go home,
where you'll feel safe.
Give me your hand...
You drive!
We shouldn't be doing this.
We're breaking the law!
- Oh, my!
- You can do it! You can make it!
We're over! We're over the bridge!
- We're over the bridge!
- We're over!
FOREST FIRE WARNING
EXTREME DANGER
- What about that sign?
- They exaggerate. We'll be fine.
Do you believe that?
Truman, we're on fire!
- It's just smoke. You okay?
- Yes.
- Wanna do it again?
- No!
Truman, stop!
What do we do for money
when we get to New Orleans?
I have my Sea haven bank card.
So we're just going to
eat into our savings, is that it?
I'll have to call your mother.
I don't know how she'll take this.
What now?
SEAHAVEN
NUCLEAR POWER STATION
- Looks like a leak at the plant.
- Back up.
Leak at the plant.
The whole area is being evacuated.
- Thank you for your help.
- You're welcome, Truman.
Truman...
Truman, come back!
Stop him!
Truman!
Stay away!
- Thank you both for your help.
- Next time he'll be charged.
I understand.
Thanks again. Good night.
Let me get you some help, Truman.
You're not well.
Why do you want to have a baby
with me? You can't stand me.
That's not true.
I'll fix you some Mococoa. Natural
cocoa beans from Mt. Nicaragua.
- No artificial sweeteners.
- What are you talking about?
I've tasted other cocoas.
This is the best.
What the hell does this
have to do with anything?
- Tell me what's happening!
- You're having a nervous breakdown.
You're part of this, aren't you?
Truman, you are scaring me.
No, you're scaring me.
What are you gonna do?
Dice me, slice me or peel me?
There's so many choices.
Do something!
What? What did you say?
- Who are you talking to?
- I didn't say anything.
- I wasn't talking to anybody.
- Talk to me!
- I don't know anything!
- Stay where you are.
Truman...?
Thank God!
How can anyone expect me to
carry on under these conditions?
It's unprofessional!
Everything's gonna be okay.
It's all gonna be fine.
I don't know what to think, Marlon.
Maybe I'm losing my mind.
It feels like the whole world
revolves around me.
That's a lot of world for one man.
Is it wishful thinking? Wishing
you'd made more out of yourself?
Who hasn't sat in the john and
had an imaginary interview on TV?
This is different.
Everybody seems to be in on it.
I've been your best friend
since we were seven.
We got through school by cheating
off each others test papers.
Jesus, they were identical.
But I always felt safe knowing that.
Because whatever the answer was,
we were right or wrong together.
I stayed up all night in your tent
so you could play North Pole.
And I got pneumonia.
Remember that?
You were out of school for a month.
You're the closest thing I ever had
to a brother, Truman.
Things haven't worked out for us
like we used to dream they would.
I know what that feeling's like.
Everything slipping away...
You don't want to believe it, so you
look for answers somewhere else.
But the point is, I'd gladly
walk in front of traffic for you.
But the point's, I'd gladly
step in front of traffic for you.
And the last thing I'd ever do
is lie to you.
And the last thing that
I would ever do... is lie to you.
I mean, think about it.
If everybody is in on it...
I'd have to be in on it, too.
I'm not in on it, Truman,
because there is no "it".
- You were right about one thing.
- What's that?
The thing that started all this.
I found him for you, Truman.
That's why I came by tonight.
I'm sure he's got
quite a story to tell.
Go to him.
Easy on the fog.
Stand by, crane-cam...
Crane-cam.
Button-cam three.
I never stopped believing.
Go wide. Curb-cam eight.
My son.
- Move in for close-up?
- No, no...
Stay back.
Fade up music.
Now go for the close-up.
All those years wasted.
I'll make it up to you, son.
I swear.
Dad...
Bravo!
Congratulations.
- Okay, quiet down. Concentrate.
- That was great television.
- Christ of, it was brilliant!
- It broke my heart.
Well done! Congratulations!
Truman drinks Mococoa,
world's finest cocoa beans -
- Grown on the upper slopes
of Mt. Nicaragua.
1. 7 billion were there
for his birth.
220 countries tuned in
for his first step.
The world stood still
for that stolen kiss.
And as he grew, so did the
technology. A human life. -
- Recorded on a network of
hidden cameras and broadcast live -
- 24 hours a day, seven days a week,
to an audience around the globe.
From Sea haven, enclosed in the
largest studio ever constructed. -
- One of only two man-made
structures visible from space. -
- Now in its 30th great year,
it's The Truman Show!
What a week! I was on
pins and needles the entire time.
I'm your host, Mike Michelson.
Welcome to True-Talk, our forum for
issues growing out of the show.
Tonight, something very special:
An exclusive interview
with the show's creator.
Let's go live to the 221stfloor
of the Omni-Cam Ecosphere.
There we'll find
the world's greatest tele-visionary.
The designer of the world within
a world that's Sea haven: Christ of.
I'd like to thank you
for granting this interview.
We know your schedule is demanding,
and how you guard your privacy.
- This, sir, is indeed an honor.
- Don't mention it.
The catalyst
for the recent dramatic events -
- Has been Truman's father, Kirk,
and his attempt at in filtration.
This is not the first time someone
has tried to reach Truman, is it?
We have had our close calls.
It's television!
I did it! I'm on The Truman Show!
But now, the first intruder
to be a former cast member.
- A dead one at that.
- Writing Kirk back in, brilliant.
Kirk started this whole crisis. He
was the only one who could end it.
Truman, no!
- That's off limits!
- Why? What's over there?
Nothing. It's dangerous, that's all.
You have to know your limitations.
Let's remind viewers why Dad was
written outin' the first place.
As Truman grew up, we manufactured
ways to keep him on the island.
- I'd like to be a great explorer.
- There's nothing left to explore.
- Then I thought up Kirk's drowning.
- He's feared the water ever since.
When Kirk read the synopsis, he was
disappointed, to say the least.
I'm sure
that's why he broke onto the set.
But how do you intend to explain
his 22-year absence?
- Amnesia.
- Brilliant.
Let's take some viewer calls. North
Carolina, you're on with Christ of.
Hi, Christ of. I was wondering how
many cameras you got in that town.
Somewhere in the vicinity of5,000.
Remember, we started with just one.
He was two weeks premature, as if
he couldn't wait to get started.
And his eagerness to leave the womb
was the reason he was selected.
In competition with five other
unwanted pregnancies -
- For a show determined by an air
date, only Truman arrived on cue.
I believe Truman is the first child
to be adopted by a corporation.
- That's correct.
- The show's made enormous revenue.
Equivalent to the GNP
of a small country.
It takes the population of an
entire country to keep it running.
Since it's on 24 hours, revenues are
generated by product placement.
Everything on the show is for sale,
down to the very homes they live in.
All of tin the Truman catalogue.
Operators are standing by.
Christ of, why has Truman
never come close to discovering -
- The true nature of his world
until now?
We accept the reality of the world
with which we're presented.
The Hague for Christ of. Hello.
The Hague...
All right,
let's go to Hollywood, California.
You're a liar and a manipulator, and
what you've done to Truman is sick.
Well, we remember this voice,
don't we? How could we forget?
- Let's go to another call.
- No, no. It's fine, Mike.
I love to reminisce
with former members of the cast.
Sylvia, as you announced so
melodramatically to the world...
Do you think because you batted
your eyes at Truman once. -
- Flirted with him,
stole a few minutes of air time -
- To thrust your politics into
the limelight, that you know him?
That you know what's right for him?
Are you in a position to judge him?
What right do you have to
turn a baby's life into a mockery?
Don't you ever feel guilty.
I have given Truman
the chance to lead a normal life.
The world, the place you live in. -
- Is the sick place. Sea haven
is the way the world should be.
- He's a prisoner, not a performer.
- He can leave at any time.
If his was more than a vague
ambition, if he was determined -
- To discover the truth, there's
no way we could prevent him.
I think what distresses you,
really, caller. -
- Is that, ultimately, Truman
prefers his cell, as you call it.
That's where you're so wrong.
And he'll prove you wrong.
These heated comments aside, it's
been a very positive experience.
For Truman and for the viewers.
Thank you for your time.
Now that this crisis is behind us. -
- Can we look forward
to some exciting new developments?
The big news is: Meryl will leave
Truman in an upcoming episode.
A new romantic interest
will be introduced.
I'm determined that TVs first
on-air conception will take place.
Another television milestone.
It has been a singular honor
and a pleasure. Christ of, thank you.
Hey, Simeon.
- Is he looking at us?
- You think he knows?
- Hello...
- Better call Christ of.
Come in, Major Burbank.
He's back to his old self.
That's an unusual cat, my man.
I hereby proclaim this planet...
...Trumania of the Burbank galaxy.
- Is he gonna go?
- Hallway camera ready.
- That one's for free.
- Stand by, all house cameras.
- Good morning.
- In case I don't see you...
...good afternoon and good night.
Good afternoon, good night...
- Morning, Truman. Hows it going?
- I'll check. Vital signs are good.
Hey, Pluto!
- Good morning!
- Look who's here.
Beautiful day, isn't it? We thought
about the policy, and we'll take it.
Great! Let's go up to my office
and sign the papers.
- Next week would be better.
- I knew it. See you guys.
- See you next week.
- Looking forward to it!
This isn't about insurance.
This is about the great variable.
When will death occur?
Could be a week, a month, a year...
Could be today.
Innocent sunbather, stabbed by
the tip of a runaway beach umbrella.
No way to guard against that.
- Excuse me.
- Truman, this is Vivian.
The two of you
are going to be neighbors.
I guess what I'm saying
is that life is... fragile.
- Vivian, your office.
- Sorry.
I'm sorry... You do?
Oh, great.
Let me take your information.
Ready, two. Go to two.
Back to medium... and wide.
I was just trying
to train the kid to... never mind.
- What's he doing in the basement?
- He moved in there when Meryl left.
Why wasn't I told? Unpredictable
behavior has to be reported.
- He's just sleeping. I thought...
- This is the best shot we've got?
- What's on the clock-cam?
- Obstruction.
- What happened?
- He was tidying up his garbage.
I was gonna call you,
but he gave up and fell asleep.
- I want to check the set-ups...
...for the insurance convention.
Nice move.
There you go.
Isolate the audio.
Give me a close-up on his torso.
Still breathing.
Where's Chloe? Call him.
Tell him it's a wrong number.
- What took you so long?
- I had to wait for it.
- They were busy. What's going on?
- I don't know.
- He did nothing but stand around.
- Shut up and watch.
Then we went to night vision.
He's asleep.
There! Stop it.
Zoom in under the chair.
- Enhance it.
- Is it...? My God...
- He didn't go up the stairs.
- Get Marlon over there!
Truman... Surprise party!
I got a six-pack of cold brew skies
with our name on them.
Come on, pal.
Come on, buddy.
Shit!
Marlon, find him.
He's still in the room.
- Come out, wherever you are.
- Good. Keep it light.
I know you're in here.
Check under the table.
The closet, behind you.
Gee, I wonder where
he could possibly be.
Lawn-cam!
- Say something. Keep it going.
- He's gone.
- Cut transmission!
- Cut transmission?
- God in heaven!
- Give me the phone!
TECHNICAL FAULT
PLEASE STAND BY
We've got every available extra
looking for him. The crew, too.
- What about prop cars?
- Accounted for.
He has the world's most recognizable
face, he can't disappear.
Go find him, Pluto. Good dog.
All this fuss!
If he could just hear my voice.
Truman! Truman!
Let me try.
Truman!
It's me, Dad!
Let's talk!
Yeah, I know. We're just about
done with the square.
We've got to go back to Barrymore,
check the interiors.
Who's watching the college?
Send someone over there.
- Take another man, get down there.
- Find the son of a bitch!
Get some batteries.
He's not gonna glow in the dark.
We need more light.
We'll never find him this way.
- What time is it?
- It's way too early for that.
Cue the sun.
What time is it?
Christ of, what's going on?
There's rumors that he's dead.
The media's having a feeding frenzy.
Every network has a pirated shot
of Marlon making an ass of himself.
- The sponsors are threatening us.
- We're getting our highest ratings.
- No sign of him.
- Go back to town, join the others.
Everyone else at first positions.
Everyone is at first positions?
He's got to be there somewhere.
- We're not watching the sea.
- Why would we watch the sea?
- Sweep the harbour.
- Bring up the harbour cameras.
- Aren't some of those out?
- Yeah, but we have the lighthouse.
All buoy-cams, please.
- Long lens, short-base cameras.
- Why are we looking at the water?
Truman, where are you going?
- Sailing? He's afraid of the water.
- Resume transmission.
I got 2-1 he doesn't make it.
Just leave them in the car.
Get off this mast-cam. You can't
see his face. Go to the cabin-cam.
Perfect.
That's our hero shot.
- Let's get another boat out there.
- I need to talk to the ferry guys.
Come on, get it moving!
- I'm just the bus driver.
- They can't sail. They're actors!
How do we stop him?
Okay... We're going to access
the weather programme' now.
So hold on to your hats.
You got that?
No, I think we'll want to
localize the storm over the boat.
Get the co-ordinates.
- There's no rescue boat.
- He'll turn back. He'll be afraid.
There she blows.
Come on.
Give me some lightning.
Hit him again!
- He can't die on television!
- He was born on television.
Hold on!
Is that the best you can do?
You're gonna have to kill me!
What should we do
with a drunken sailor...
- I demand you cease transmission.
- Keep running.
Increase the wind!
- For the last time...
- Capsize him, tip him over.
- He's tied himself to the boat!
- He'll drown, and he doesn't care.
Do it... Do it!
That's enough.
I want to talk to him.
EXIT
Truman... You can speak.
I can hear you.
- Who are you?
- I'm the creator of a TV show.
It gives hope
and inspiration to millions.
- Then who am I?
- You're the star.
- Was nothing real?
- You were real.
That's what made you so good
to watch. Listen, Truman.
There's no more truth out there
than in the world I created for you.
The same lies, the same deceit.
But in my world,
you have nothing to fear.
- I know you better than you do.
- You never had a camera in my head.
You're afraid.
That's why you can't leave.
It's okay, Truman.
I understand.
I have been watching you
your whole life.
I was watching when you were born.
I was watching
when you took your first step.
I watched you
on your first day of school.
The episode
when you lost your first tooth.
You can't leave, Truman.
- Please, God.
- You belong here.
You can do it.
With me.
Talk to me.
Say something.
Say something, damn it! You're
on TV. You're live to the world!
In case I don't see you,
good afternoon and good night.
He made it!
All right, Truman!
Cease transmission.
- You want another slice?
- No. Let's see what else is on.